Guide to the Kōji Nakanishi papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Kōji Nakanishi papers
1949-2010
Nakanishi, Kōji, 1925-
34 linear ft. (34 record storage cartons)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1540
7906287
Biographical Note
Koji Nakanishi is a bioorganic chemist and Columbia University professor emeritus of chemistry.
Nakanishi was born in Hong Kong on May 11, 1925. He attended Nagoya University where he received his bachelor's, and later his PhD in chemistry. Nakanishi did post-graduate work at Harvard University before returning to Japan where he taught chemistry at a number of Universities.
Nakanishi joined the faculty of Columbia University in 1969 where he taught chemistry and established a natural-products research lab. He and remained part of Columbia's chemistry department for the rest of his career. In 1980 he became the Centennial Professor of Chemistry and is currently a professor emeritus.
Nakanishi's career has focused largely on animal and human vision, including studies intended to accelerate the development of a treatment for macular degeneration. With his current group of graduate students, he is also studying the effects of gingko biloba extract on neurological disorders.
He has received numerous awards and prizes for his scientific work, and the Nakanishi Prize awarded jointly by the American Chemical Society and the Chemical Society of Japan is names in his honor.
Koji Nakanishi has two children, three grandchildren, and is an enthusiastic amateur magician.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of the professional papers of Koji Nakanishi. The files contain correspondence with collaborators, graduate students, and others in the scientific community; files related to patents owned by Nakanishi; and subject files highlighting Nakanishi's scholarly interests and scientific pursuits throughout his career.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 4 series
Series I: Subject Files
Series II: Correspondence
Series III: Publications
Series IV: Patents
Subjects
Columbia University.--Dept. of Chemistry.; Nakanishi, Kōji, 1925-; Bioorganic chemistry.; Chemistry, Organic.; Gingko.; Vision.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least two business days in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
Koji Nakanishi Gift 08/01/2010, 2010.2011.M007
- Series I: Subject/Alphabetical Files
  The subject files series is the largest series in the collection. This series contains files related to Nakanishi's scholarly work, professional service, and awards and recognition that he received for his own scientific work. There are also many subject files that reflect his scholarly interests, particularly his long interest in the potential of ginkgolides for improving vision and memory and his work with Biosphere and Biosphere 2.
  - Retinoids (Box 1)
  - VCD-Vision (Box 1)
  - PAFR (Box 1)
  - Insect Vision (Box 1)
  - Retnioids (Box 1)
  - Fish Vision (Box 1)
  - "Overall"/Vision (Box 1)
  - Ret-proteins (Box 1)
  - Cyclopropyl 6-5-locked (Box 1)
  - G-Protein (Box 1)
  - Transduction (Box 1)
  - Vision (New) (Box 1)
  - Rhodopsin (Box 1)
  - A2-E: Original Manuscripts-Manuscript, Fax, Letter (Box 1)
  - A2-E Eye Chemistry-Eye Science on RPE (Box 1)
  - A2-E (Box 1)
  - A2E-AMD (Box 2)
  - A2E/Lipofuscin-Fluorecsent Pigments in RPE (Box 2)
  - A2E Proposals (Box 2)
  - A2E/Faxes/Phone #5 (Box 2)
  - A2E Misc. (Box 2)
  - Ginkgolides (Box 2)
  - Ginkgo-2 (Box 2)
  - A2E (Box 2)
  - A2E (Box 2)
  - A2E-Oxid. (Box 2)
  - A2E-Quercetin (Box 2)
  - Vision/ 36564 GM (Box 2)
  - Vision/ 36564 GM-Woody Rh Paper (Box 2)
  - Rh/A2E (Box 2)
  - PAFR-2 (Box 2)
  - Vision-Shichida (Box 2)
  - Vision-Shichida (own papers) (Box 2)
  - A2E Papers-others (Box 3)
  - A2E-AMD Heidi (Box 3)
  - A2E Antioxidants (Box 3)
  - A2E-Lipotuscin (Box 3)
  - A2E-AMD (Box 3)
  - Rh Misc. (Box 3)
  - Rh-3: G Protein (Box 3)
  - Rh-2 (Box 3)
  - Rh-2-Vision Papers (Box 3)
  - Rhod. Publications (Box 3)
  - Visual Pigment Papers (Box 3)
  - CD (Box 3)
  - Dr. Wang, Zhi Yuan (CU)-Dermato/tea (Box 3)
  - Natural Products (Box 3)
  - Hemoglobin (Box 3)
  - Dictyostelum (Box 3)
  - Dictyostelum-Rich Kessin (Box 3)
  - Dictyostelum-Slime Molds, Other Species (Box 3)
  - BPP (Box 3)
  - Porphyrin/DNA (Box 3)
  - Photoaffinity Labeling (Box 3)
  - HB Hemoglobin (Box 4)
  - Marine (Fusetani) (Box 4)
  - Pheromones (Box 4)
  - Mitomycin (Box 4)
  - Sphigolipids (Box 4)
  - Folk Medicine (Box 4)
  - DNA (Box 4)
  - DNA (Box 4)
  - FTIR Mitomycin CJ Rh/bR (Box 4)
  - BTX (Box 4)
  - Sugar (Publications) (Box 4)
  - Reptile (Box 4)
  - NP Papers (Box 4)
  - Memory (Box 4)
  - PAF Gingko (Box 4)
  - Rhodopsin (Box 4)
  - Gingkolide Biosynthesis (Box 4)
  - GLU-R (Box 4)
  - GLU-R (Box 4)
  - PAF (Box 4)
  - Memory (Box 5)
  - Memory (Box 5)
  - GABAR (Box 5)
  - AD-1 (Box 5)
  - AD-2 (Box 5)
  - UV of Arom. Compounds (Box 5)
  - Sugar (data/own paper) (Box 5)
  - NMR, T1, T2 Overhead (Box 5)
  - Spin Systems, T1, T2 (Box 5)
  - NMR (Box 5)
  - MAS-NMR (Box 5)
  - MS (BTX) (Box 5)
  - Phys. Const. Tables (Box 5)
  - MS (Box 5)
  - MS VCD (Box 5)
  - CPC/Cytosensor (Box 5)
  - COX-Z (Box 5)
  - CD (Box 5)
  - Peptides CD (Box 5)
  - CD 1-5 (Box 6)
  - CD 6/'97 (Box 6)
  - CD-KN (Box 6)
  - CD (Exciton Chirality) (Box 6)
  - CD (Box 6)
  - CD (benzylic etc) OLD (Box 6)
  - CD (Box 6)
  - Stereochem (Box 6)
  - Exciton Chirality Literature (Box 6)
  - Tandem MS/BTX MS (Box 6)
  - 19F-SS NMR (Box 6)
  - Alt. Mcd (Box 6)
  - Cytosensor (Box 6)
  - Bioactive (Box 6)
  - History of Natural Products (Box 6)
  - Dr. J.N. Wu (Box 6)
  - Kronenberg (Box 6)
  - Taxol (Box 6)
  - Bioactive-NatiProd Lit. (Box 6)
  - Bioactive (Box 6)
  - Pfiesteria Toxin (Box 7)
  - DBA (Box 7)
  - Ascidian (Box 7)
  - Psi Factor (Box 7)
  - Tunichromes (Box 7)
  - Tunichromes (Box 7)
  - Tubulin (Box 7)
  - Hand-outs (Box 7)
  - 4141 MC BTX (Box 7)
  - 4141 (old) (Box 7)
  - 8141 Material (Box 7)
  - Reviews (Box 7)
  - General Interest (Box 7)
  - General Interest (Box 7)
  - CD (1982 Fall) (Box 7)
  - ROA (Box 7)
  - Ancient Lecture Notes (Box 7)
  - G8248 (Box 8)
  - Ancient Participation Lists (Box 8)
  - n-Ach-R (Box 8)
  - Active Grants: NSF CD (Box 8)
  - CD ('89 & earlier) (Box 8)
  - NMR Lecture (Box 8)
  - 8141 Fall 1884 (Box 8)
  - G4172 (Box 8)
  - Chemistry C3443x Spring '84 (Box 8)
  - G4141x (1976/77) (Box 8)
  - Rhodopsin Reviews (Box 8)
  - ir Raman (Box 8)
  - MS (Box 8)
  - Topics (Box 9)
  - Odajima (Box 9)
  - Chi-Huey Wong (Box 9)
  - Ur pK (Box 9)
  - Ginkgolides (Box 9)
  - Topics in Natural Products (Box 9)
  - 13c NMR Literature Xeroxs (Box 9)
  - Finished Seminars (Box 10)
  - Conferences (Box 10)
  - Archive (Box 10)
  - Awards (Box 10)
  - Awards (Box 10)
  - Awards (Box 10)
  - Clippings (Box 10)
  - Org. Spectroscopy (Box 10)
  - Org. Spectroscopy (Box 10)
  - Itochu (Box 10)
  - Japanese Letters (Box 10)
  - Active Collaboration/ Frequent Correspondence-Tubulin (Box 10)
  - Active Collaboration/ Frequent Correspondence (Box 10)
  - American Chemical Society (Box 10)
  - Editorships (Box 10)
  - Lecture Pamphlets (Box 10)
  - Conferences (Box 10)
  - Publication Guidelines (Box 10)
  - Publications in Press (Box 10)
  - Publications Submitted (Box 11)
  - Publication Plans (Box 11)
  - Referee Correspondence (Box 11)
  - Science Watcher-Papers in Preparation (Box 11)
  - Amazon 2 (Box 11)
  - Brazil I (Box 11)
  - Brazil II (Box 11)
  - Private (Box 11)
  - CD (Box 11)
  - The Chemical Record (Box 11)
  - Czech Academy (Box 11)
  - IPSEN (Box 11)
  - Japan Chemical Society (Box 11)
  - JASCO (Box 11)
  - John Wiley (Box 11)
  - Maruzen Models (Box 11)
  - Nobel Prize Nominations (Box 11)
  - NatProd (Box 11)
  - Nuskin (Box 11)
  - SAB (Box 11)
  - SMART (Box 11)
  - Sunbor (Box 11)
  - Suntory (Box 11)
  - Tokyo Kagaku Dozin (Box 11)
  - University Books (Box 11)
  - Wyeth-Ayerst Res. (Box 11)
  - PhTX Analogs (Box 12)
  - PhTX Analogs-Own Papers (Box 12)
  - PhTX Papers-Own Papers (Box 12)
  - PhTX Papers (Box 12)
  - Polyamine Toxins (Box 12)
  - Glutamate (Box 12)
  - n-Ach-R (Box 12)
  - Glutamate (Box 12)
  - Philanthotoxin (Box 12)
  - HIF (Box 12)
  - HIF (Box 12)
  - Glu Own Papers (Box 13)
  - Glu Own Papers-Neurophysiol (Box 13)
  - HIF (Box 13)
  - HIF-Photoaffinity ATPase (Box 13)
  - HIF (Box 13)
  - HIF Transparancies (Box 13)
  - Therajem (Box 13)
  - Ojima KN Slides (Box 13)
  - Gonick "HIF" (Box 13)
  - Ecdysones Papers (Box 13)
  - Ecdysones (Reviews) (Box 13)
  - HIF (Box 13)
  - Peter Cohen (Box 13)
  - Ginkgolide (Box 13)
  - KOWA Company (Box 13)
  - KANEKA (Box 13)
  - Merck (Box 13)
  - Molecumetics (Box 13)
  - New York Botanical Garden (Box 13)
  - New Chemical Entities (Box 13)
  - MS (Box 13)
  - Nittobo (Box 13)
  - PROBEM (Box 13)
  - Contracts (Box 14)
  - Research Biochemicals International (Box 14)
  - Riken (Box 14)
  - Sequoia (Box 14)
  - Sanki Laboratories (Box 14)
  - Cloning (Box 14)
  - NP Novemeber 2004 (Box 14)
  - Princess Chulabhorn (Box 14)
  - Usherwood, Peter (Box 14)
  - Plantaceutica (Box 14)
  - Nakanishi Prize (Box 14)
  - Nakanishi Prize 1997 (Box 14)
  - ASP Award (Box 14)
  - Dreyfus (Box 14)
  - King Faisal Prize (Box 14)
  - Nominations (Box 14)
  - Welch Award (Box 14)
  - Berova (Box 14)
  - Chemistry Library (Box 15)
  - CV-Scientists (Box 15)
  - CV-Scientists (Box 15)
  - MS Facilities (Box 15)
  - Obituaries (Box 15)
  - Seeking Positions (Box 15)
  - Undergraduates (Box 15)
  - Contracts Pending (Box 15)
  - KN-80 (Box 15)
  - 34509 Proposals (Box 15)
  - 34509-1 (Box 15)
  - AMB (Box 15)
  - Chemistry Department (Box 15)
  - Ancient Reprints (Box 16)
  - CD/Bioactive GM 34509 (Box 16)
  - Companies for Instruments for CD Proposal GM 34509 (Box 16)
  - CD NIH34509 (Box 16)
  - Donations (Box 16)
  - Failed Proposals (Box 16)
  - Funding (Box 16)
  - Ginkgolides (Box 16)
  - Progess Reports Ginkgo (Box 16)
  - Ginkgo Bilberry (Box 16)
  - ESNAP Report (Box 16)
  - Granting Agencies (Box 16)
  - Group Finance (Box 16)
  - Makiko Files (Box 16)
  - OUABAIN/HL52282 (Box 16)
  - Proposals (Box 16)
  - Phytoalexins (Box 16)
  - Vision 2002-GM 36564 (Box 16)
  - MH 068817 Ginkgolide (Box 16)
  - Rhodopsin-Vision Final Report (Box 16)
  - HFSP (Box 17)
  - Old Grant Materials (Box 17)
  - Old Grant Materials-NIH 36564 (Vision) (Box 17)
  - Bioorganic/Receptor AI 10187 (Box 17)
  - Retinal/Retinoid Letters, Projects (Box 17)
  - Ceroplastes (Box 17)
  - Brevetoxin (Box 17)
  - Insects (Box 17)
  - Trichilin/Akita Data (Box 17)
  - Trigonelline (Box 17)
  - Misc. Reprints (Box 17)
  - IR (Box 17)
  - 50 Reprints (Box 17)
  - Personal (Box 17)
  - Patent: Cape (Box 17)
  - Patent: Glutatmate (Box 17)
  - Patent: Misc. (Box 18)
  - Patent: Sugar (Box 18)
  - Patent Wyeth (Box 18)
  - Biosphere 2 (Box 18)
  - 4172/2003 Vision (Box 18)
  - CAPE (Box 18)
  - Chlamydomonas 1 (Box 18)
  - Chlamydomonas 2 (Box 18)
  - IR/RAMAN/UV (Box 18)
  - Spectroscopy Mixed (Box 18)
  - NMR Book (Box 18)
  - UV Second Deriv. (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 18)
  - Misc. Lit. (Box 19)
  - Visual Pigment and bR Slides (Box 19)
  - Antheridiogen Slides (Box 19)
  - G2 Factor-Bell "Sugar" (Box 19)
  - Icipe Slides (Box 19)
  - Periplanone (Box 19)
  - Abscisc Acid Slides (Box 19)
  - Y Base Slides (Box 19)
  - Abs. Config. (Chicago) (Box 19)
  - Sunbor (Box 19)
  - Mitomycin (Box 19)
  - Mitomycin-clippings (Box 19)
  - Chlamydomonas Salamander (Box 19)
  - Retroretinoids (Box 19)
  - BTX (Box 19)
  - Eye 5 Folding (Box 19)
  - Rh 8 (Box 19)
  - Rh 8-Bleaching Adaptation (Box 19)
  - EYE 2 (early) (Box 19)
  - Retinol (Box 19)
  - Yukari Thesis (Box 19)
  - Rongyuan Xie (Box 19)
  - GM 10187 (Box 20)
  - GM 10187 March2001 (Box 20)
  - Pending Collaboration (Box 20)
  - Ginkgolides NIH-November 2001 (Box 20)
  - 2-& 3-dehydro ecdysone (Box 20)
  - 9-13-bromo (Box 20)
  - Sugar Chirality (Box 20)
  - Antifeedants (Box 20)
  - Insect Sliders (Box 20)
  - Azadirachtin (Box 20)
  - Bleaching Adaptation (Box 20)
  - BTX (Box 20)
  - BTX (Box 20)
  - Cabenegrin (Box 21)
  - CPC (Box 21)
  - Propolis (Box 21)
  - Collision Activation MS (Box 21)
  - Ecdysone Receptor (Box 21)
  - Ecdysone Receptor (Box 21)
  - FAB (Box 21)
  - Folding (Box 21)
  - Hopanoids (Box 21)
  - Imidazoline Receptors (Box 21)
  - IR Master (Alan Croteau) (Box 21)
  - Kuroyanagi (Nambu) (Box 21)
  - MIH Papers (Box 21)
  - MIH (Box 21)
  - Alternative Medicine (Box 21)
  - Snake Venom (Box 21)
  - Matsuno/ Propolis (Box 21)
  - Pharmanex (Box 22)
  - Pharmanex (Box 22)
  - Hamamatsu (Box 22)
  - IAP (Box 22)
  - IPII (Box 22)
  - JICA (Box 22)
  - Sci-Tech Center NSF (Box 22)
  - NSF 01-29 Biosphere (Box 22)
  - Biosphere 2 (Box 22)
  - Bioorganic Studies of Retinal Proteins-Vision NIH (Box 22)
  - Photoaffinity Labeling of Rhodopsin-Irini Zanze NRSA (Box 22)
  - The CD Excition Chirality Method and Its Applications NIH (Box 22)
  - Parking and Hotels (Box 22)
  - Financial (Box 22)
  - Group: Payroll (Box 22)
  - Group: Housing Memos (Box 22)
  - Benefits/Insurance (Box 22)
  - Accounts (Box 22)
  - Misc: Owned to KN (Box 22)
  - Chemical Abstracts Service (Box 22)
  - Muscarinic Acetylchol Rec (Box 22)
  - OBI (Box 22)
  - Photoacoustic IR (Box 22)
  - Polyene Macrolide (Box 22)
  - Porphyrins (E. Vogel) (Box 22)
  - Protein Peptides (Box 22)
  - Rapamycin (Box 22)
  - Rapamycin (Box 22)
  - Rapamycin (Box 23)
  - 2H Rhod. (Box 23)
  - SHARK (Box 23)
  - SP-303 (Box 23)
  - Spisula Oocytes (Box 23)
  - Sugar (Box 23)
  - Thomas Biosynthesis (Box 23)
  - Visual Transduction (Box 23)
  - VIT. A (Box 23)
  - "The Chemistry of Vision" (Box 23)
  - RIKEN I (Box 23)
  - RIKEN II (Box 23)
  - Hess (Box 23)
  - Maarten (Box 23)
  - Dr. Schachter (Box 23)
  - WITKOP (Box 23)
  - Checkbook (Box 23)
  - Studies on Bioactive Compounds and Receptors NIH (Box 23)
  - Account Book (Box 23)
  - ALCON (Box 23)
  - MBI (Box 23)
  - Memory (Box 23)
  - Travel (Box 23)
  - Drawer Account-1989 receipts (Box 24)
  - Drawer Account-1988 receipts (Box 24)
  - ACS Reimbursements 8/90 (Box 24)
  - Drawer Account-1990 receipts (Box 24)
  - Drawer Account-1991 receipts (Box 24)
  - Laura Eisenstein (Box 24)
  - Rhodopsin Overheads (Box 24)
  - BION (Box 24)
  - Berkowitz, B. (Box 24)
  - LE Overheads (Box 24)
  - LE Book (Box 24)
  - Bristol-Myers Squibb (Box 24)
  - Ret Proteins (Box 24)
  - Larex (Box 24)
  - Millennium (Box 24)
  - OBI (Box 25)
  - Pharmanex (Box 25)
  - KAST (1998) (Box 25)
  - Nominations-Horne, McDerm (Box 25)
  - Nominations-RB (Box 25)
  - Univ. System (Box 25)
  - Univ. System (Box 25)
  - Wandering Nat. Prod. Chem. (Box 25)
  - Finished Seminars 1984-1985-1986 (Box 25)
  - Shaman Pharmaceuticals (Box 26)
  - Pharmanex (Box 26)
  - Pharmanex (Box 26)
  - Theragem (Box 26)
  - Nakanishi Symposium (Box 26)
  - Nakanishi Symposium Thank You Letters (Box 26)
  - Nakanishi Symposium Address Corrections (Box 26)
  - KN 70th Celebration (Box 26)
  - KN 70th Celebration-Heterocycles (Box 26)
  - KN 70th Celebration-Papers Dedicated to KN (Box 26)
  - Welch Festivities (Box 26)
  - Spring Seminars '97 (Box 26)
  - ACAD (1/2) (Box 26)
  - ACAD (2/2) (Box 26)
  - Misc. (Box 27)
  - Symposiums (Box 27)
  - Finished Seminars (1982-1994) (Box 27)
  - Finished Seminars (1994-1996) (Box 27)
  - Misc. (Box 27)
  - Chemistry Department (Box 27)
- Series II: Correspondence
  The correspondence series includes correspondence with friends and collaborators in the scientific community, as well as correspondence relating to awards and prizes.
  - Alphabetical Correspondence, (4 folders) (Box 28)
  - Probem: Boston Mtg. (Box 28)
  - Probem (Box 28)
  - Berkovich (Box 28)
  - John Prezzuto (Grant) (Box 28)
  - Alphabetical Correspondence (Box 28)
  - Awards '93-'95 (Box 29)
  - Awards '95-'98 (Box 29)
  - Finished Seminars '98 (Box 29)
  - Old Correspondence-Individuals (filed '98) (Box 29)
  - East Asia Council (Box 29)
  - Nakanishi Prize (Box 29)
  - NMR Book Protest '95 (Box 29)
  - IR Book '98 (Box 29)
  - Jones and Bartlett (Box 29)
  - Grad. Students, (2 folders) (Box 29)
- Series III: Publications
  The publications series includes copies of Nakanishi's journal articles and other published work, as well as offprints of articles by others.
  - Publications 1-80 (missing #1) (Box 30)
  - Publications 81-159 (Box 30)
  - Publications 160-239 (missing #161, 175, 214, 229) (Box 30)
  - Publications 240-320 (Box 30)
  - Publications 321-377 (Box 30)
  - Publications 378-426 (missing #418, 420, 425) (Box 30)
  - Publications 427-519 (missing #448, 474, 481) (Box 30)
  - Publications 575-632 (Box 30)
  - Publications 633-680 (Box 31)
  - Publications 681-730 (Box 31)
  - Publications 731-765 (Box 31)
  - Publications 766- (Box 31)
  - Articles and Offprints by Others, (11 folders) (Box 31)
- Series IV: Patents
  The patents series includes files related to numerous patents worked on or held by Koji Nakanishi. This series also includes files for grants and other sponsored research.
  - Round Table (Box 32)
  - PAS (Box 32)
  - Wood (Box 32)
  - KAZU (Box 32)
  - Bell (Box 32)
  - Pseudrelone (Box 32)
  - Prof. Nozoe (Box 32)
  - Patent 1-201 (Box 32)
  - Patent 1-201 (Box 32)
  - Patent 1-202 (Box 32)
  - Patent 1-202 (Box 32)
  - Patent 7402-Ginkgolides (Box 32)
  - Illudin-S (Box 32)
  - PN-B (Box 32)
  - Finished Seminars '83-'84 (Box 32)
  - US-Japan January '84 (Box 32)
  - C15 Ginkgolide (Box 33)
  - 4-04 Isoxazole (Box 33)
  - Obsolete Grants-Past Grants: Navy N62269-78-C-0368 (Box 33)
  - Obsolete Grants-Past Navy Grant: N00014-80-C-0578 6/1/80-5/31/81 (Box 33)
  - Obsolete Grants-Past Grants: AI 10187 + CA11572 FTIR Supplement (Box 33)
  - Obsolete Grants-US/Japan Seminar Corr. (Box 33)
  - C20 Gingkolide (Box 33)
  - HV Synthesis (Box 33)
  - Cuauntemone (Box 33)
  - Cervicarcin (Box 33)
  - Flouroscene (Box 33)
  - Ginkgolides (Box 33)
  - Task Force II (Box 33)
  - Benzoate Chirality (Box 33)
  - NAF (Box 33)
  - Lycopodine (Box 33)
  - X Base (Box 33)
  - Abscisin (Box 33)
  - TG (Box 33)
  - Inactive Grants (Box 34)